What else will it be, Jale?
Jale, ¿Qué más te doy?
JALE: Give me another pound of chuck, please.
Jale: Otra librita de morrillo.
Another one of chuck?
¿Otra de morrillo?
JALE: Due to our economic situation we lived in a zone that wasn't apt...
Jale: Por la situación económica, vivíamos en una zona no apta para habitar,
to raise the children. Because the river was right there,
ni para tener niños. Cerca de un riachuelo,
so it was full of mosquitoes and it was very cold.
había muchos zancudos y mucha humedad.
So, because of that, they caught bronchopneumonia and pneumonia.
Por esa razón, la bronconeumonía y la neumonía,
The children.
atacaba a los niños.
I lost four children in that time, due to pre-eclampsia,
Fueron cuatro niños que perdí en esa época por culpa de la preclamsia.
so the doctors told me that if the children were born alive,
Los médicos me decian que si los niños nacían vivos...
that if they saved the baby, I died, or all the way around: If I died, the baby got saved.
si se salvaba el niño, yo moría. O viceversa.
And in case both of us made it through the birth,
Si nos salvábamos los dos en el parto,
the baby wouldn’t last more than four months.
Los bebés no vivirían más de cuatro meses.
And so it happened, four months later they died.
Y así fue. A los cuatro meses amanecían muertos.
Oh no.
¡Ay no!
That’s very hard, Jale, losing a baby that young.
Es muy duro Jale, que a uno se le muera un niño así pequeño.
If such a young baby hurts that much, how would it be if it was an older one, right?
Si un niño así pequeño duele tanto, ¿Cómo será un hijo grande, ¿Cierto?
— Oh, he’s pissed, he’s pissed. — He’s hungry.
— ¡Ay! se enojó, se enojó! — Tiene hambre.
— Give him the pacifier, the pacifier. — Where is it?
— ¡El biberón! — ¿Dónde está?
I think they didn’t bring it, I don’t know.
No lo trajeron. No sé.
—They didn’t bring it…? — Who has Jerónimo’s pacifier!?
— No lo trajeron. — ¿Quién tiene el biberón de Geronimo?
WOMAN: Finally!
Señora: ¡Finalmente llegó!
— Come, come. — How's it goin'?
— ¡Ven! — ¿Cómo estás?
This is my other sister.
Ella es la otra hermana.
When my babies died…
Cuando mis niños murieron…
Back in Chocó they have this custom...
Se acostumbraba en el departamento del Chocó…
...because children don’t have any sins...
...como los niños no han pecado,
People do a Gualí.
hacer un Gualí.
Gualí means we sing and dance for the kids while they are in their little coffin.
Un gualí es cantar y bailar para el niño en el ataúd.
In the little coffin, like this, and it’s like a dance,
En el ataúd, si. Es un baile.
to cradle the baby, even if they’re dead.
para arrullar el niño después de muerto.
LADY: The ones that sang were not the parents, not the ones mourning.
Abuela: Los que cantaban no eran los padres. Los dolientes no.
The mourners were crying, and the rest were singing, and dancing.
Los dolientes estaban llorando y los demás cantando y bailando.
Because…you let them because the baby’s dead, and that way they’re supposed to go to Heaven,
Porque de esa manera el niño va al cielo,
And the reason for this is joy, because the baby goes to Heaven.
Era la razón de nuestra alegría, saber que se iba al cielo.
I don’t know.
¡Yo no sé!
WOMAN: I’ve always told her: “Sister, always keep going. Never give up. Always keep going.”
Mujer: Yo siempre le he dicho a ella: "Hermana, para adelante es para allá, para atrás ni para coger impulso"
And she always says “The same goes to you, sister.”
Y ella siempre responde: "Lo mismo le digo hermana."
We have always understood each other. Always, always.
Nosotras siempre nos hemos comprendido. ¡Siempre, siempre!
I admire her work.
Yo admiro su trabajo.
— I admire it. And I respect her. I respect her. — And I feel proud of her. Proud of her.
— Yo le admiro su trabajo y la respeto. — Y me siento orgullosa de ella.
Play some music!
¡Pongan música!